<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-pinder-integrity-md-00"
     category="info"
     consensus="false"
     submissionType="independent"
     version="3"
     tocInclude="true"
     tocDepth="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="INTEGRITY.md">
      INTEGRITY.md: A File Format for Sub-Enterprise AI Product Trust Self-Mapping
    </title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-pinder-integrity-md-00"/>

    <author fullname="Tom Pinder" initials="T." surname="Pinder">
      <organization>Startvest LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hampstead, NC</street>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>integrity@theintegrityframework.org</email>
        <uri>https://theintegrityframework.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2026" month="May" day="18"/>

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>Independent Submission</workgroup>

    <keyword>integrity</keyword>
    <keyword>trust</keyword>
    <keyword>ai</keyword>
    <keyword>compliance</keyword>
    <keyword>verifiability</keyword>
    <keyword>self-attestation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document describes INTEGRITY.md, a plain Markdown file format for
        publishing self-mapped product trust artifacts. INTEGRITY.md addresses
        a gap in the existing trust-artifact ecosystem: small software products
        (typically priced under five thousand US dollars in annual recurring
        revenue per customer) for which audited control frameworks such as
        SOC 2 are economically and structurally inappropriate. The format is
        a six-section self-mapping against the Layer 1 vetoes of an underlying
        framework specification, designed to be reachable at a stable URL, free
        of authentication, and verifiable mechanically by third parties.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document is for informational purposes and does not propose an
        IETF standard.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>
        The market for software product trust artifacts has bifurcated. At the
        enterprise tier, audited frameworks such as SOC 2, ISO 27001, and the
        NIST Cybersecurity Framework provide buyers with third-party attestation
        backed by recurring audits. At the consumer tier, browser sandboxing
        and platform-level controls perform much of the trust work without
        product-side participation.
      </t>

      <t>
        The intermediate tier, comprising small business and team-purchased
        software in the approximate range of twenty to two hundred United States
        dollars per month and under five thousand US dollars in annual recurring
        revenue per customer, is poorly served by either extreme. The cost of a
        first-time SOC 2 audit (typically twenty to one hundred thousand US
        dollars per year) exceeds plausible product revenue at this tier. The
        buyer in this tier is not a procurement officer but a single department
        head or team lead; the time available to evaluate a vendor is measured
        in minutes, not weeks.
      </t>

      <t>
        Existing alternatives have known failure modes. Vendor-authored "trust
        pages" without supporting artifacts are unverifiable. Pay-for-badge
        services produce a credential without altering the underlying behavior.
        Generic privacy policies do not address product-specific concerns such
        as use of third-party AI sub-processors.
      </t>

      <t>
        INTEGRITY.md is a file format for publishing a self-mapped trust artifact
        at a stable URL. It is the textual surface of a separately-published
        framework specification (the Integrity Framework, see
        <xref target="TIF-V1"/>) but is independent of that framework's
        governance: any party may fork the format, publish a competing
        framework, and produce INTEGRITY.md files mapped against that fork.
      </t>

      <section anchor="conventions">
        <name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
        <t>
          The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and
          "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
          when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
        <t>
          The following terms are used in this document:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>INTEGRITY.md</dt>
          <dd>
            The file format defined in this document. By convention the file is
            named <tt>INTEGRITY.md</tt> in mixed case.
          </dd>
          <dt>Framework</dt>
          <dd>
            A separately-published specification enumerating the vetoes,
            constraints, and guardrails an INTEGRITY.md self-maps against. This
            document defines the file format; it does not define a specific
            framework.
          </dd>
          <dt>Veto</dt>
          <dd>
            A pre-build trust check defined by the underlying framework. The
            framework referenced in this document defines six Layer 1 vetoes,
            but the file format is agnostic to the number.
          </dd>
          <dt>Self-mapping</dt>
          <dd>
            The product operator's own assessment of conformance with a veto,
            stated as one of "Pass", "Pass with disclosed conflict", or "Fail
            with disclosed trade-off".
          </dd>
          <dt>Verifier</dt>
          <dd>
            A third party reading the INTEGRITY.md file to make a trust
            decision. Typically a prospective buyer; may also be a public
            directory operator or an automated crawler.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="format">
      <name>File Format</name>

      <section anchor="encoding">
        <name>Encoding and Location</name>
        <t>
          An INTEGRITY.md file <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be encoded as UTF-8
          <xref target="RFC3629"/> Markdown
          (<xref target="CommonMark"/> or a compatible flavor).
        </t>
        <t>
          The file <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be reachable at a stable URL without
          authentication. The <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> locations, in order
          of preference, are:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li>For open-source products: at the repository root, alongside
          README.md.</li>
          <li>For closed-source products: at the path <tt>/integrity.md</tt> or
          <tt>/integrity</tt> on the canonical product website (i.e., the
          domain a buyer would discover via standard search).</li>
          <li>At <tt>/.well-known/integrity.md</tt> on the canonical product
          domain.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          The file <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be served with a
          <tt>Content-Type</tt> of <tt>text/markdown; charset=utf-8</tt>
          (<xref target="RFC7763"/>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="header">
        <name>Required Header</name>
        <t>
          The file <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> begin with an H1 heading naming the
          product (for example <tt># INTEGRITY.md — &lt;Product name&gt;</tt>).
          Following the heading, the file <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a
          metadata block stating, at minimum:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>Product name and canonical URL.</li>
          <li>Operator (legal entity).</li>
          <li>Framework specification and version evaluated against
          (as a URL).</li>
          <li>Self-evaluation tier (if the framework defines tiers).</li>
          <li>Date last updated (ISO 8601 <xref target="RFC3339"/>).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          The metadata block <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be expressed as bolded
          key-value pairs (Markdown emphasis) to aid both human and automated
          parsing.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="veto-sections">
        <name>Veto Sections</name>
        <t>
          The body of the file <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain one section per
          veto defined by the referenced framework. Each veto section
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li>Be introduced by an H3 (or deeper) heading naming the veto.</li>
          <li>Begin with a one-line outcome statement chosen from "Pass",
          "Pass with disclosed conflict", or "Fail with disclosed trade-off".</li>
          <li>Include at least one paragraph of plain-text explanation. The
          explanation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be specific to the product; generic
          marketing language is non-conformant.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          A veto section <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include additional artifact links
          (to a methodology page, a public repository, a third-party review, or
          comparable evidence). Links <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> resolve to publicly
          reachable URLs.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="optional-sections">
        <name>Optional Sections</name>
        <t>
          A file <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include sections beyond the required vetos,
          including but not limited to:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>Architectural constraints (Layer 2 in the framework referenced
          here).</li>
          <li>Operational guardrails (Layer 3 in the framework referenced
          here).</li>
          <li>A changelog enumerating prior versions of the file.</li>
          <li>A statement of license under which the file is published. A CC
          BY 4.0 <xref target="CCBY40"/> license is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>
          to permit verifier redistribution and analysis.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="example">
      <name>Example</name>
      <t>
        The following is a minimal conformant INTEGRITY.md self-mapped against
        a fictional three-veto framework. A full six-veto example mapped
        against the Integrity Framework v1.0 is available at
        <eref target="https://theintegrityframework.org/integrity-md"/>.
      </t>

      <sourcecode type="markdown">
<![CDATA[
# INTEGRITY.md — ExampleProduct

**Product:** ExampleProduct (https://example.test)
**Operator:** Example Corp.
**Framework version evaluated against:** 1.0 (https://example-framework.test/v1)
**Self-evaluation tier:** Bronze
**Last updated:** 2026-05-18

---

## Layer 1 vetoes — self-mapping

### Veto 1 — Artifact versus outcome

**Pass.**

ExampleProduct sells outcome (working product, measurable by the buyer)
not artifact (a badge or report). No certification language appears on
the marketing site disconnected from the actual product behavior.

### Veto 2 — Independence

**Pass with disclosed conflict.**

Example Corp. operates the verification directory and is also a listee
for its own product. This is a material conflict, disclosed on each
listing page with a footnote linking back to this section.

### Veto 3 — Verifiability

**Pass.**

Public artifacts: source repository at https://github.com/example/product,
changelog at https://example.test/changelog (versioned and dated), and
this INTEGRITY.md.

---

## Changelog

- 2026-05-18 — Initial publication against v1.0.

---

*Published under CC BY 4.0.*
]]>
      </sourcecode>
    </section>

    <section anchor="verification">
      <name>Verification Procedure</name>
      <t>
        A verifier evaluating an INTEGRITY.md file <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>:
      </t>
      <ol>
        <li>
          Fetch the file at its stated canonical URL. The fetch
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> succeed without authentication.
        </li>
        <li>
          Verify the file begins with an H1 product-name heading and a
          metadata block as defined in <xref target="header"/>.
        </li>
        <li>
          Verify each veto section is present, has a recognized outcome
          statement, and contains product-specific explanation.
        </li>
        <li>
          For each artifact URL referenced in a veto section, verify the URL
          resolves to publicly reachable content. The verifier
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> record any URLs that fail to resolve and
          surface them in any downstream report.
        </li>
        <li>
          Where the underlying framework defines tier requirements, verify
          the self-evaluation tier matches the artifacts presented (e.g., a
          Silver claim requires the Silver-tier artifacts named in the
          framework).
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>
        A verifier <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> implement automated checks for the steps
        above. The reference implementation
        (<eref target="https://github.com/Startvest-LLC/startvest-integrity-cli"/>)
        performs structural validation and URL resolution against an
        INTEGRITY.md file.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        INTEGRITY.md is a self-authored trust artifact. A verifier
        <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> treat it as equivalent to an audited
        attestation. The format's value lies in producing a fixed, public
        surface against which a verifier can apply their own scrutiny;
        the responsibility for that scrutiny rests with the verifier.
      </t>
      <t>
        Operators publishing an INTEGRITY.md <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be aware
        that the published file becomes part of the public record. Statements
        made in the file are admissible in subsequent disputes about
        product behavior. Cosmetic statements (those that pass the textual
        test of the format but fail to address product-specific concerns)
        are likely to be cited adversely in such disputes.
      </t>
      <t>
        Verifiers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be aware that artifact URLs cited
        in an INTEGRITY.md may change after the file is fetched. A
        snapshot-and-archive workflow is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> for any
        verifier intending to act on the file's contents at a later time.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document does not specify any cryptographic mechanism for
        binding an INTEGRITY.md to a specific operator. Such mechanisms
        (for example, signed commits in a repository, or DNS-based domain
        verification) are out of scope and are left to operators and
        verifiers to negotiate.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This document has no IANA actions.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner"/>
          <date year="1997" month="March"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174">
        <front>
          <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
          <author fullname="B. Leiba" initials="B." surname="Leiba"/>
          <date year="2017" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3629" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3629">
        <front>
          <title>UTF-8, a transformation format of ISO 10646</title>
          <author fullname="F. Yergeau" initials="F." surname="Yergeau"/>
          <date year="2003" month="November"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="63"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3629"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3339" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3339">
        <front>
          <title>Date and Time on the Internet: Timestamps</title>
          <author fullname="G. Klyne" initials="G." surname="Klyne"/>
          <author fullname="C. Newman" initials="C." surname="Newman"/>
          <date year="2002" month="July"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3339"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC7763" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7763">
        <front>
          <title>The text/markdown Media Type</title>
          <author fullname="S. Leonard" initials="S." surname="Leonard"/>
          <date year="2016" month="March"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7763"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>

      <reference anchor="TIF-V1" target="https://theintegrityframework.org/framework/v1">
        <front>
          <title>The Integrity Framework v1.0</title>
          <author fullname="Tom Pinder" initials="T." surname="Pinder">
            <organization>Startvest LLC</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2026" month="April"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CommonMark" target="https://spec.commonmark.org/0.31.2/">
        <front>
          <title>CommonMark Specification</title>
          <author fullname="J. MacFarlane" initials="J." surname="MacFarlane"/>
          <date year="2024" month="January"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CCBY40" target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
        <front>
          <title>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Creative Commons</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
        The Integrity Framework, including the six Layer 1 vetoes referenced
        in this document, was developed by Startvest LLC in early 2026 as a
        response to the trust-artifact gap for sub-enterprise software
        products. The format described here is the textual surface of that
        framework, abstracted to permit independent forks.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
